Joseph Cornell
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Ephemera and Artifacts, 1858-1946, Series 5:; (boxes 18, 23; 0.8 linear feet)
  - Cartes-de-visite, 1867-1873 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - Autograph Book (mostly blank), circa 1893 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - Sheet Music, "Summer Girl Song," 1896 (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - Leather Postcards, 1906, undated (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - Dried Bouquet, circa 1940 (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Dried Flowers from Lawrence Farm, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - Cabinet Cards, undated (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - Hat Pins, undated (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - Miniature Rug Samples, undated (Box 18, Folder 29)
  - Song Recording (broken), undated (Box 18, Folder 30)
  - Tobacco Trade Cards and Designs, undated (Box 18, Folder 31)
  - Victorian Cards, undated (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - Victorian Valentine Card, undated (Box 18, Folder 33)
  - Loose Objects, undated, (3 small boxes and 1 item; not scanned) (Box 23)
    First small box contains:
    Moth specimen in small rectangular box (with a note from Benton attached, indicating that she intended to give it as a gift to Lane [Faison])
    Papier-mache pull-toy horse with notes in square cardboard box
    Stuffed bird figures, matchboxes, plastic toy, clockhands, and metal pendents in small round box
    Box containing cloth from the funeral car and flowers from the funeral wreath of Ulysses S. Grant (with notes identifying material and indicating that it was "presented by Rev. Stephen Merritt")
    Second small box contains:
    Paperweight, container of buttons, wood and cork pieces, wooden beads, piece of driftwood, and small bell in square cardboard box
    Metal grasshopper figure
    Third small box contains:
    Metal pencil case (rusted)
    Plastic dolls
    Shell box
    Item: Round wooden box (6-3/4" in diameter)
- Photographs, circa 1905-1972, Series 6:; (boxes 18, 28; 0.3 linear feet)
  Series consists of artist and art work photographs, family photographs, photographs by and of various individuals, and publicity photographs from the New York City Ballet. Artist photographs include photocopies of ones of Cornell and ones of the sculptor, Lee Bontecou, taken by Hans Namuth. Namuth's photographs of Cornell, including some of the photocopied ones found here, were featured in the book, American Masters: The Voice and the Myth by Brian O'Doherty. Art work photographs include a photograph of one of Cornell's commercial projects (Still Life for Good Housekeeping), and stats of Robert Cornell's drawings, some of which Cornell may have used in the series of memorial collages he created after Robert's death. Family photographs include childhood images of Cornell with various members of his family, an image of Cornell as a student, a childhood image of Robert Cornell and photographs of Robert as an adult and his train collection, photographs of Cornell's mother later in life, and what seem to be various photographs of nieces and nephews. Also found are photographs taken by friends and acquaintances of Cornell, including Wayne Andrews, David Gahr, Harry Roseman, and Terry Schutte, as well as photographs of various friends, including Marcel Duchamp, Tilly Losch, and Mina Loy.
  Unidentified photographs are arranged in a file at the end of the series. Additional photographs can be found amongst correspondence and subject source files.
  - Artist Photographs, Cornell by Hans Namuth (photocopies), [1972], (See Box 28) (Box 18, Folder 34)
  - Artist Photographs, Lee Bontecou by Hans Namuth, undated, (See Box 28) (Box 18, Folder 35)
  - Art Work Photographs, Still Life by Cornell for Good Housekeeping, 1952, (See Box 28) (Box 18, Folder 36)
  - Art Work Photographs, Robert Cornell's Drawings, 1967, undated (Box 18, Folder 37)
  - Family Photographs, House in Nyack Where Cornell Was Born, undated (Box 18, Folder 38)
  - Family Photographs, Helen Cornell and children, circa 1905, (See Box 28) (Box 18, Folder 39)
  - Family Photographs, Joseph I. Cornell, undated (Box 18, Folder 40)
  - Family Photographs, Cornell Family, circa 1915 (Box 18, Folder 41)
  - Family Photographs, Cornell, circa 1921 (Box 18, Folder 42)
  - Family Photographs, Robert Cornell as a child, undated (Box 18, Folder 43)
  - Family Photographs, Robert Cornell and his train collection, 1948, 1965, undated (Box 18, Folder 44)
  - Family Photographs, Helen S. Cornell, circa 1960s (Box 18, Folder 45)
  - Family Photographs, Miscellaneous, 1967, undated (Box 18, Folder 46)
  - Photograph Album Page, "Froehlich Homestead," circa 1955, (See Box 28) (Box 18, Folder 47)
  - Photograph by Wayne Andrews, [1968] (Box 18, Folder 48)
  - Photographs by David Gahr, undated (Box 18, Folder 49)
  - Photograph by Harry Roseman, undated (Box 18, Folder 50)
  - Photographs by Terry Schutte (See also Series 4), 1965 (Box 18, Folder 51)
  - Photograph of Marcel Duchamp, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 52)
  - Photographs of Tilly Losch (See also Series 4), undated (Box 18, Folder 53)
  - Photographs of Mina Loy, undated (Box 18, Folder 54)
  - Photographs of Children (Schoelkopf and Smillie), undated (Box 18, Folder 55)
  - Publicity Photographs of the New York City Ballet, undated (Box 18, Folder 56)
  - Unidentified Photographs, undated (Box 18, Folder 57)
  - Oversized, Artist Photographs, Cornell by Hans Namuth, [1972], (See Box 18, F34) (Box 28 (sol))
  - Oversized, Artist Photographs, Lee Bontecou by Hans Namuth, undated, (See Box 18, F35) (Box 28 (sol))
  - Oversized, Art Work Photographs, Still Life by Cornell for Good Housekeeping, 1952, (See Box 18, F36) (Box 28 (sol))
  - Oversized, Family Photographs, Helen S. Cornell and children, circa 1905, (See Box 15, F39) (Box 28 (sol))
  - Oversized, Photograph Album Page, "Froelich Homestead," circa 1955, (See Box 18, F47) (Box 28 (sol))
- Art Works, circa 1966-1971, Series 7:; (boxes 19, 23; 0.2 linear feet)
  Series consists of several unfinished collages and Rorschachs (or ink blot drawings) by Cornell, two collages by his sister, Betty Cornell Benton (who signed her work as Betty Voohr), on which Cornell collaborated by adding images, and a box by Christine Kaufman (wife of the actor, Tony Curtis), which was a gift to Cornell.
  Some art work can also be found amongst correspondence. For Walter De Maria's portfolio, Chicago Project, 1968, see the Walter De Maria correspondence file.
  This bulk of this series has been scanned with the exception of the box by Christine Kaufman.
  - Unfinished Collages, 1971, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Includes note by Benton, and some annotations by both Cornell and Benton.
  - Rorschachs (Ink Blot Drawings) (See also Series 4), 1968-1971, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Collages by Betty Voohr with additions by Cornell, undated, (2 folders) (Box 19, Folder 3-4)
  - Box by Christine Kaufman (Curtis), circa 1966, (Not scanned) (Box 23)
- Books and Printed Material, 1806-1968, Series 8:; (boxes 19, 23; 0.5 linear feet)
  Series consists of several books, and various publications and clippings collected by Cornell apart from that which he accumulated as source material.
  The books found here most likely comprise the remainder of Cornell's library, which was transferred to the Joseph Cornell Study Center, Smithsonian American Art Museum. They reflect some of Cornell's wide-ranging interests, including Christian Science, astronomy, and literature. Notable ones include a copy of Nevertheless, inscribed to Cornell and signed by the author, Marianne Moore; a copy of New Testament - Psalms, which appears to have been a gift to Cornell from his mother; and a copy of Sylvie - Recollections of Valois by the French author, Gerard de Nerval, whose writing had a tremendous influence on Cornell. Some of the books actually seem to have belonged to Cornell's sister, Betty Cornell Benton, including one of the copies of Christian Science and Its Discoverer, and Christina Rossetti's Poems, which appears to have been a gift from Cornell.
  Printed material includes booklets and publications that likewise reflect Cornell's interest in Christian Science, as well as his interest in art and ballet. Found are magazines with articles on other artists and a copy of Allison Delarue's privately-printed monograph on Henry Wikoff, the impressario who brought the Austrian dancer, Fanny Elssler, to America in the 1840s. Printed material also includes clippings and press releases relating to exhibitions of Cornell's art work at New York University (1963) and the Guggenheim Museum (1967), as well as a copy of the December 1957 issue of Art News, which featured an article on Cornell and which includes his annotations indicating his negative reaction to how he was portrayed.
  Books and printed material are arranged chronologically. For descriptive purposes, books are treated as one file with a list of titles (provided below).
  This series is partially scanned. Books have not been digitized and only covers, title pages and/or relevant pages of other printed materials have been scanned.
  - Books 1806-1967, undated, (Not scanned) (Box 23)
    Titles include:
    Celebrated Women Travellers of the Nineteenth Century, W.H. Davenport Adams (1883)
    Christian Science and Its Discoverer, E. Mary Ramsey (1935) (2 copies)
    Comet Lore, Edwin Emerson (1910)
    Legends of the Rhine, H.A. Guerber (1895)
    Nevertheless, Marianne Moore (1944)
    New Testament - Psalms (undated)
    Poems by Christina Rossetti (1953)
    The Poetical Works of John Milton, Vol. II (1806)
    Star Names and Their Meanings, R.H. Allen (1936)
    The Story of Flushing, Cornwall, Ursula Redwood (1967)
    Sylvie - Recollections of Valois, Gerard de Nerval (1887)
  - Christian Science Booklets, 1904-1966 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1946, 1964, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Magazines, Articles on Other Artists, 1948, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Art News, Article on Cornell, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Cornell Exhibit at New York University, 1963 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Cornell Exhibit at Guggenheim Museum, 1967, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
    Includes handmade card from Paul Waldman (See also Series 2).
  - The Chevalier Henry Wikoff, Impresario 1840 by Allison Delarue, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 11)
- Writings about Cornell, 1950, circa 1975-1980, Series 9:; (box 19; 0.3 linear feet)
  Series consists of writings about Cornell's art work. Included is an article by the poet, Mina Loy (who was a friend and admirer), which represents a writing by one of Cornell's contemporaries. It is not clear where, or even whether, this article was published. The copy found here is a typescript which Loy appears to have shared with Cornell, containing revisions (perhaps by Cornell) in pencil. Other writings include copies of various theses, presentations, and articles stemming from research on Cornell conducted by several graduate students in art history. These individuals were in contact with Betty Cornell Benton in the process of doing their research (See Series 10 for their correspondence), and they ended up sending her copies of the final products. These graduate student writings represent some early examples of Cornell scholarship in the field of art history.
  Files are arranged chronologically. This series has been scanned in entirety.
  - Loy, Mina, "Phenomenon in American Art" (typescript), 1950 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Friend, Sherry, "Joseph Cornell: Sun in the Snow," Manuscript, circa 1975 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Friend, Sherry, "Joseph Cornell: Sun in the Snow," Illustrations, circa 1975, (4 folders) (Box 19, Folder 14-17)
  - Haroutunian, Helen, "Joseph Cornell's Medici Slot Machine," 1978, (2 folders) (Box 19, Folder 18-19)
  - Haroutunian, Helen, "Joseph Cornell's Medici Slot Machine," Thesis Presentation, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - Haroutunian, Helen, "Cornell in View," 1980 (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - Young, Vivian, "Joseph Cornell in Context," undated (Box 19, Folder 22)
- Joseph Cornell Estate Papers, circa 1911, 1944-1986, Series 10:; (boxes 19-22; 3.5 linear feet)
  Series is comprised primarily of correspondence, legal documents, and printed material created and accumulated by Betty Cornell Benton in her role as residuary legatee of Cornell's estate, as well as some miscellaneous family papers. Estate papers relate to Benton's administration of the part of Cornell's estate for which she was responsible and her various legal disputes with the executors of the estate. They shed light, to a certain extent, on the exhibition and sale of Cornell art works, as well as on the disposition of Cornell material, during the period of time after his death and up until the mid-1980s. Estate papers document Benton's efforts to safeguard the memory of Cornell and to foster the memory of their brother, Robert, who was often wrongly portrayed as being mentally disabled; to carry on Cornell's legacy by contributing to charitable institutions and donating art works to museums and universities; and to organize and appropriately dispose of Cornell's papers, books, records, and source material. They also document the relationships Benton forged with some of Cornell's friends and acquaintances, as well as with curators, museum directors, collectors, dealers, and artists.
  The Joseph Cornell Estate Papers series is arranged as four subseries:
  10.1: Correspondence, 1954-1986
  10.2: Legal Files, 1966-1968, 1973-1983
  10.3: Printed Material, 1944-1982
  10.4: Miscellaneous Family Papers, circa 1911, 1944-1964
  The bulk of this series has been scanned with the exception of printed materials such as books, magazines and exhibition catalogs for artists other than Cornell; typically only covers, title pages, and/or relevant pages of these items have been digitized.
  - Correspondence, 1954-1986, 10.1:
    Subseries consists of correspondence sent and received by Benton in the administration of Cornell's residual estate, as well as some printed material and photographs that were accumulated in the same files. Correspondents include: lawyers, collectors, dealers, galleries, museums, curators, scholars, writers, art critics, artists, admirers of Cornell, the executors of Cornell's estate, and charitable institutions, as well as some of Cornell's former "helpers," friends, and acquaintances.
    Correspondence generally relates to the exhibition, loan, appraisal, auction, and sale of Cornell art work. It documents, in particular, Cornell exhibitions at the ACA Galleries, Art Institute of Chicago, Castelli Feigen Corcoran Gallery, Hopper House, Washburn Gallery, and Washington University in St. Louis; and the major Cornell retrospectives, "Joseph Cornell" at the Museum of Modern Art (November 1980-January 1981) and "Joseph Cornell: An Exploration of Sources" at the National Museum of American Art (November 19, 1982-February 27, 1983). Correspondence also relates to the disposition of Cornell material and art work, including donations of his papers, books, records, and/or source material to various cultural institutions (such as the Anthology Film Archives, Museum of Modern Art, Archives of American Art, and National Museum of American Art, among others), and gifts of art work to various museums and galleries (such as Meadow Brook Art Gallery at Oakland University, Mead Art Gallery at Amherst College, and Williams College Museum of Art, among others). Correspondence also concerns Benton's gifts of art work (particularly, collages and book objects), source material, memorabilia, and copies of some of Cornell's papers to various individuals.
    Correspondence documents Benton's many efforts to continue Cornell's legacy and to preserve his memory, including her monetary donations to charitable institutions in memory of her brothers; her attempts to correct misinformation and misrepresentations of Cornell and his family published in various articles (as in a letter to New York Magazine correcting a mistake about the nature of Robert's handicap in an article written by Thomas Hess); and her concern to have the right person do a "Cornell book" (as reflected in correspondence with Wayne Andrews, Dore Ashton, Lynda Roscoe Hartigan, Diane Waldman, and Don Windham). Correspondence also documents her role in facilitating research on Cornell, including that of graduate students, such as Sherry Friend and Helen Haroutanian (See also Series 9), and that of scholars such as David Porter; her work organizing and cataloging Cornell's papers and source material; and the various requests she fielded for information about or authentication of certain Cornell works.
    Benton organized the correspondence into files according to correspondent, and the files in alphabetical order according to name of institution or surname of individual. Items in each file were typically accumulated in reverse chronological order. When only a few items were associated with a correspondent, Benton organized these into general alphabetical files. The existing organization has, for the most part, been maintained.
    - ACA Galleries (Sidney and Pearl Bergen), 1975-1977 (Box 19, Folder 23)
    - Ader, Richard, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 24)
    - Albright-Knox Art Gallery, 1972, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - American Dovecote and Shooting Gallery (Castelli Feigen Corcoran Gallery), 1977-1982, undated (Box 19, Folder 26)
    - Andrews, Wayne and Lisa, 1972-1974, undated, (2 folders) (Box 19, Folder 27-28)
    - Anthology Film Archives, 1976-1983, undated, (3 folders) (Box 19, Folder 29-31)
    - Art Institute of Chicago, 1982-1983 (Box 19, Folder 32)
    - Ashton, Dore, 1973, undated (Box 19, Folder 33)
    - A, 1954, 1973-1980, undated (Box 19, Folder 34)
    - The Bedside Network (See also Series 2 and 11), 1973-1980 (Box 19, Folder 35)
    - Behringer, Hurley and Hurley (See also Subseries 10.2), 1973-1978, (3 folders) (Box 19, Folder 36-38)
    - Bellevue Hospital Center, 1973-1977 (Box 19, Folder 39)
    - Bennette, George and Shirley (Lighthouse Music School), 1973-1976 (Box 19, Folder 40)
    - Bergman, Edwin and Lindy, 1975-1983, undated (Box 19, Folder 41)
    - Bergman, Robert, 1975-1983, undated (Box 19, Folder 42)
    - Bishop, Elizabeth, 1974-1978 (Box 19, Folder 43)
    - Brown, Jo, 1979-1981, undated (Box 19, Folder 44)
    - B, 1973-1981, 1986, undated (Box 19, Folder 45)
    - Campbell, Mariruth, 1973-1974 (Box 19, Folder 46)
    - Carrithers, Dorcas, 1977 (Box 19, Folder 47)
    - Charles Hamilton Galleries, 1981 (Box 19, Folder 48)
    - Corcoran, James, 1976-1979 (Box 19, Folder 49)
    - Coulter, Dorothy, 1973-1976 (Box 19, Folder 50)
    - C, 1974-1983, undated (Box 19, Folder 51)
    - Demetrion, James, 1973-1983, undated, (3 folders) (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
    - Dorazio, Virginia, 1973-1975 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - D, 1974-1977 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Ethe, Solomon, 1974-1977, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - E, 1973-1975 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - First Church of Christ, Scientist, Bayside, 1973, 1977-1980 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Fourcade, Droll Inc. (See also Subseries 10.2), 1973-1976, (4 folders) (Box 20, Folder 9-12)
    - Friend, Sherry, 1975-1978 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - F, 1965, 1976-1981, undated (Box 20, Folder 14)
      Includes letters from Edward Flower, who was the lawyer for Helen Batcheller.
    - Guggenheim Museum, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Gussow, Alan, 1977-1981 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - G, 1973-1979 (Box 20, Folder 17)
      Includes letters from the Gallery Association of New York State, Inc. and Henry Geldzahler (Metropolitan Museum of Art).
    - Halper, Edward and family, 1973-1984, undated, (4 folders) (Box 20, Folder 18-21)
    - Haroutanian, Helen, 1977-1982 (Box 20, Folder 22)
    - Hartigan, Lynda Roscoe (See also National Museum of American Art), 1975-1983, 1986, undated, (5 folders) (Box 20, Folder 23-27)
    - Hartigan, Lynda Roscoe, "Special Folder," 1983-1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 20, Folder 28-29)
    - Hirschhorn Museum and Sculpture Gallery, 1981-1983, undated (Box 20, Folder 30)
    - Historical Society of Rockland County, 1963, 1972-1974 (Box 20, Folder 31)
    - Hopper House (The Edward Hopper Landmark Preservation Foundation), 1977-1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 20, Folder 32-33)
    - Hussey, Howard, 1972-1978 (Box 20, Folder 34)
    - H, 1972-1978 (Box 20, Folder 35)
    - Indiana, Robert, 1975-1977 (Box 20, Folder 36)
    - Johnson, Ray, 1977, 1984, undated (Box 20, Folder 37)
    - J, 1976-1979 (Box 20, Folder 38)
      Includes letter from Larry Jordan alluding to his film on Cornell.
    - Kahn, Max, 1975-1983 (Box 20, Folder 39)
    - Kappel, Hugh, 1973-1976, 1981, undated (Box 20, Folder 40)
    - K, 1973-1980 (Box 20, Folder 41)
      Includes letters from Yayoi Kusama (with some annotations by Betty Cornell Benton), Rolf Koppel, and Kraushaar Galleries, and a handmade Christmas card from Allegra Kent.
    - Lane, Alvin S., 1975 (Box 20, Folder 42)
    - League in Aid of Crippled Children, 1973-1979, (2 folders) (Box 20, Folder 43-44)
    - Licka, Sean, 1977-1983, undated (Box 20, Folder 45)
    - L, 1973-1982 (Box 20, Folder 46)
      Includes letter from Jean Farley Levy (wife of Julien Levy) and brief correspondence with Tanaquil LeClerq.
    - MacWhinnie, John, 1980, undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Includes art work by MacWhinnie.
    - Museum of Modern Art, 1973-1974, 1980, undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Myers, John Bernard, 1973-1976, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - M, 1973-1984, undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Includes letters from MD Medical News Magazine, Tom Messer (Guggenheim Museum), and the Minnesota Historical Society.
    - National Museum of American Art (formerly National Collection of Fine Arts and currently Smithsonian American Art Museum), 1974-1983, (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 5-6)
    - National Museum of American Art, Exhibition (See also Hartigan, Lynda Roscoe), 1982-1984, (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 7-8)
    - New York Institute for the Education of the Blind, 1973-1975 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Noble, Alastair and Lindsay, 1982-1983, undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Novak, James, 1976, undated (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - N, 1973-1979 (Box 21, Folder 12)
      Includes letters from Hans Namuth and copies of Betty Cornell Benton's letters to the editors of New York Magazine and the New York Times (clearing up a point about the legal dispute between the family and executors discussed in an article by Hilton Kramer).
    - Oakland University (Meadow Brook Art Gallery),1984-1985 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Paine, Stephen, 1973-1977 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Parke Bernet, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Philatelic Hobbies for the Wounded, 1967-1970, 1976 (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - The Phillips Collection, 1975-1976 (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - Plandome Book Auctions, 1976 (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - Porter, Aline, 1975-1981 (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Porter, David, 1976-1981 (Box 21, Folder 20)
    - P, 1973-1978, undated (Box 21, Folder 21)
      Includes letters from the Philadelphia Museum of Art (Anne d'Harnoncourt), Anne and Fairfield Porter, and Eve Propp (a former "helper").
    - Queens Museum (formerly Queens County Art and Cultural Center) (See also M file), 1973-1982 (Box 21, Folder 22)
    - Roseman, Harry, 1973-1978 (Box 21, Folder 23)
    - R, 1974-1977 (Box 21, Folder 24)
    - Smithsonian Institution, 1973-1983, (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 25-26)
    - Southampton College, 1974-1977 (Box 21, Folder 27)
    - Stiglitz, Ruth, 1973-1976 (Box 21, Folder 28)
    - Szyncer, Katherine Sergava, 1973-1978 (Box 21, Folder 29)
    - S, 1973-1981, undated (Box 21, Folder 30)
      Includes letters from Terry Schutte, Lewis Shepard (Department of Fine Arts, Amherst College), and Sandra Starr.
    - Tate Gallery, 1974 (Box 21, Folder 31)
    - T, 1973, 1976 (Box 21, Folder 32)
      Include letter from Dickran Tashjian.
    - University of Massachusetts, 1976-1977 (Box 21, Folder 33)
    - U, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 34)